Guide to the Palo Alto Stock Farm Records SC0006
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Palo Alto Stock Farm records
1875-1913
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Palo Alto Stock Farm (Stanford, Calif.)
SC0006
27.5 Linear Feet (58 boxes)
Records of Leland Stanford's Santa Clara county property, the Palo Alto Stock Farm (devoted to the breeding and training of trotting horses) and Tehama County property, the Vina Ranch (primarily a vineyard and winery with some horse breeding facilities.) Includes correspondence, letter books, auction catalogs, daily journals, stud records, farm records, breeding registers, time books, foal records, maps and employee records of the Palo Alto Stock Farm and winery, and clippings about the Stock Farm. Correspondents include L. Brodhead of the Woodburn Farm in Kentucky; John S. Clark, a breeder in New Jersey; William B. Fasig & Co., auctioneers in Cleveland, Ohio; J. Malcolm Forbes; and Peter C. Kellogg & Co., auctioneers in New York.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Associated Materials
Related materials in the Stanford University Archives include the Stanford Family Papers (SC0033).
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Palo Alto Stock Farm comprised the major farming properties of Senator Leland Stanford. The first property of the Palo Alto Stock Farm was purchased in 1876 from George Gordon; later additions increased its size to approximately 8000 acres. The Stock Farm later became the site of Stanford University. Vina Ranch, a 55,000 acre ranch, was purchased by Leland Stanford between 1881 and 1885. The Ranch was sold in 1919.
Description of the Collection
Records of Leland Stanford's Santa Clara County property, the Palo Alto Stock Farm (devoted to the breeding and training of trotting horses) and his Tehama County property, the Vina Ranch (primarily a vineyard and winery with some horse breeding facilities.) Includes correspondence, letter books, auction catalogs, daily journals, stud records, farm records, breeding registers, time books, foal records, maps and employee records of the Palo Alto Stock Farm and winery, and clippings about the Stock Farm. Correspondents include L. Brodhead of the Woodburn Farm in Kentucky; John S. Clark, a breeder in New Jersey; William B. Fasig & Co., auctioneers in Cleveland, Ohio; J. Malcolm Forbes; and Peter C. Kellogg & Co., auctioneers in New York.
Catalogs (auction); Clippings.; Wine and wine making.; Horse breeders.; Horses -- Stud-books.; Maps; Journals.; Studbooks.; Registers.; Marvin, Charles; Palo Alto Winery (Calif.); Forbes, J. Malcolm; Kellogg, Peter C.; Lathrop, Ariel; Palo Alto Stock Farm (Stanford, Calif.); Lathrop, Charles.; Palo Alto Stock Farm (Stanford, Calif.); Brodhead, L.; Clark, John S.; Stanford, Leland; Reynolds, O. N.; Vina Ranch (Calif.)
- Catalogs (auction and sales), 1882-1889 (Box 1)
- Catalogs (auction and sales), 1890-1893 (Box 2)
- Catalogs (auction and sales), 1894-1898 (Box 3)
- Catalogs (auction and sales), 1898-1904 (Box 4)
- Letterbook, 1882 Jan 27-1884 Oct 8 (Box 5)
- Letterbook, 1886 Feb 22-Jul 6 (Box 5)
- Letterbook, 1886 Jul 7-Dec 20 (Box 5)
- Letterbook, 1886 Dec 20-1887 Jun 22 (Box 5)
- Letterbook, 1885 Jun 26-1886 Feb 20 (Box 6)
- Letterbook, 1886 Mar 14-1886 Jun 5 (Box 6)
- Letterbook, 1887 Jun 20-1887 Dec 20 (Box 6)
- Letterbook, 1887 Dec 19-1888 Mar 14 (Box 6)
- Letterbook, 1888 Jun 6-1888 Dec 20 (Box 7)
- Letterbook, 1888 Dec 23-1889 Feb 26 (Box 7)
- Letterbook, 1889 Jun 29-1890 Feb 12 (Box 7)
- Letterbook, 1890 Feb 13-1890 Sep 27 (Box 7)
- Letterbook, 1890 Sep 29-1891 May 21 (Box 8)
- Letterbook, 1891 May 20-1891 Sep 25 (Box 8)
- Letterbook, 1891 Sep 24-1892 Jan 18 (Box 8)
- Letterbook, 1892 Jan 18-1892 Aug 4 (Box 8)
- Letterbook, 1892 Aug 5-1893 Mar 30 (Box 9)
- Letterbook, 1893 Mar 30-1893 Dec 12 (Box 9)
- Letterbook, 1893 Dec 14-1894 Aug 2 (Box 9)
- Letterbook, 1894 Aug 3-1894 Dec 31 (Box 10)
- Letterbook, 1895 Jan 1-1895 Apr 25 (Box 10)
- Letterbook, 1895 Apr 25-1895 Sep 16 (Box 10)
- Letterbook, 1895 Sep 17-1896 Feb 11 (Box 10)
- Letterbook, 1896 Feb 12-1896 Jun 16 (Box 11)
- Letterbook, 1896 Jun 16-1896 Dec 28 (Box 11)
- Letterbook, 1896 Dec 23-Apr. 24, 1897 (Box 11)
- Letterbook, 1897 Apr 26-1897 Sep 16 (Box 11A)
- Letterbook, 1897 Sep 17-1898 Feb 18 (Box 12)
- Letterbook, 1898 Feb 18-1898 Jun 23 (Box 12)
- Letterbook, 1898 Jun 23-1898 Dec 3 (Box 12)
- Letterbook, 1898 Dec 22-1899 May 1 (Box 12)
- Letterbook, 1899 May 2-1899 Oct 9 (Box 13)
- Letterbook, 1899 Oct 9-1900 Feb 27 (Box 13)
- Letterbook, 1900 Feb-Jun 25 (Box 13)
- Letterbook, 1900 Jun 27-Nov 13 (Box 13)
- Letterbook, 1900 Nov 13-1901 Mar 25 (Box 14)
- Letterbook, 1901 Mar 25-Jul 23 (Box 14)
- Letterbook, 1901 Jul 24-Dec 10 (Box 14)
- Letterbook, Frank W. Covey, 1892 Mar-1899 Jun (Box 14)
- Business letters, incoming, A - B (Box 15)
- Business letters, incoming, Q - Z (Box 16)
- Business letters, chronologically arranged, 1888-1890 (Box 17)
- Business letters, chronologically arranged, 1891-1894 (Box 18)
- Business letters, chronologically arranged, 1897-1902 (Box 19)
- Business letters, chronologically arranged, 1898-1902 (Box 20)
- Stake records (Box 21)
- Farm leases and contracts, 1876-1901 (Box 22)
- Farm leases and contracts, 1880-1901 (Box 23)
- Inventory, 1893 and 1895 (Box 54)
- Blacksmith department, 1898 (Box 54)
- Daily Journal, 1887 (Box 24)
- Stock on hand, 1896 (Box 24)
- Produce raised on Palo Alto lands, 1898-1900 (Box 24)
- Blacksmith department, shoeing, 1892-1895 (Box 24)
- Ledger, 1875-1887 (Box 25)
- Farm ledger (with some winery information), 1885-95 (Box 25)
- Cash accounts, 1896-1898 (Box 25)
- Stud fee payments, 1877-1881 (Box 25)
- Feed account, 1890 (Box 25)
- Board account, 1894-96 (Box 25)
- Stake record (Box 25)
- Breeding registers, 1877-1883 (Box 26)
- Breeding registers, 1884-1892 (Box 27)
- Breeding registers, 1893-1899 (Box 28)
- Breeding registers, 1900-1905 (Box 29)
- Daily journal, 1877-1883 (Box 30)
- Daily journal, 1884-1887 (Box 31)
- Requisitions, 1883-1893 (Box 32)
- Requisitions, 1883-1903 (Box 33)
- Ledgers, 1885-1891 (Box 33)
- Records of purchases, sales, deaths, and foals (Box 34)
- Records of purchases, sales, deaths, and foals (Box 35)
- Time books (Box 36)
- Time books (Box 37)
- Palo Alto and running horse sample breeding books (Box 38)
- Palo Alto and Vina foals (Box 39)
- Palo Alto stock raised (Box 39)
- Bill of sale copy-book (Box 40)
- Foal record by stud (Box 40)
- General accounts, 1897-1902 (Box 41)
- General accounts, 1886-1888 (Box 41)
- Cash books, 1897-1898 (Box 41)
- Order book, 1875-1884 (Box 41)
- Order book, 1885-1886 (Box 41)
- Horse record of families, including Electioneer's harem, 1877-1878 (Box 41)
- Horse records (4 volumes) (Box 41)
- Mr. Ariel Lathrop's stake record (Box 41)
- Due dates of stakes (Box 41)
- Account of grain stored at Coutts' place, 1883 (Box 41)
- Stock book, 1870s and 1880s (Box 42)
- Record of Electioneer and family, 1895 (Box 42)
- Horse record (Box 42)
- Classified record book of Palo Alto horses at Vina, 1893 (Box 42)
- List of stock shipped to various destinations, 1891-1897 (Box 42)
- Employees' board memo, 1897-1901 (Box 42)
- Record of [railroad?] tickets issued to employees, inventory, list of employees, and other information, 1880s (Box 42)
- Receipt books stubs, 1892, 1895-98, 1900-01 (Box 42)
- Vina stock (Box 43)
- Geldings and foals sent to Vina, 1878-1888 (Box 43)
- Palo Alto Winery day books and miscellaneous information (Box 44A)
- Pages from a visitors register, 1883-1884 (Box 44A)
- Copy book, letters, 1884-1885 (Box 44B)
- Catalog mailing lists (Box 45)
- Brood mares sent to Vina (Box 45)
- Vina foals, 1885 (Box 45)
- Verification of horses and stock on hand, 1894 (Box 45)
- Stakes, 1884-1885 (Box 45)
- Miscellaneous unsorted recordbooks (Box 45)
- Folder of materials re pedigrees and history of 6 Stanford horses (Box 45)
- Inventory of Francisquito cottage (Box 46)
- Farewell to manager O. N. Reynolds from employees (Box 46)
- Pedigree charts (Box 46)
- Thoroughbreds sold at Madison Square Garden, 1899 (Box 46)
- Package of letters relating to wool at Vina, 1913 (Box 46)
- Inventory PASF and Vina, 1900 (Box 46)
- PASF, register of white men who have been or are employed (Box 46)
- Miscellaneous unsorted papers (Box 46)
- Miscellaneous unsorted papers (Box 46)
- Vina breeding records (Box 47)
- Vina herd registers (Box 48)
- Vina herd registers (Box 49)
- Clippings concerning the Stock Farm
  - San Francisco Examiner, "Palo Alto Trotters", 1891 Jan 27 (Box 50)
  - San Francisco Call, "Yearlings at Auction", 1896 Nov 13 (Box 50)
  - The Strand Magazine, "A Cemetery for horses", 1901 Dec (Box 50)
  - San Francisco Chronicle, "Palo Alto", 1881 Nov 20 (Box 50)
  - Record Union, "An Equine Paradise", 1889 Sep 24 (Box 50)
  - The Harness Horse, article on Charles Marvin, 1947 Dec 10 (Box 50)
  - California Sports, "The Heyday of the Horse", 1926 Mar (Box 50)
  - Palo Alto Times, "Trainer visits old haunts", 1952 Nov 6 (Box 50)
  - The Horse Review, "Airplane Flight Over Palo Alto", 1928 Dec 12 (Box 50)
- Stock Farm ledger in account with A. M. Carrel, 1898-1900 (Box 50)
- Stock Farm ledger in account with A. M. Carrel, 1898 (Box 50)
- General time book, 1902 Jun 1-1903 Jan 30 (Box 50)
- General time book, 1902 Jan-May (Box 50)
- Office directory, undated (Box 50)
- General time book, 1903 Feb (Box 50)
- Board account of men employed at Palo Alto farm, 1902 Apr 1-1903 Jan (Box 50)
- By-laws and rules and regulations of the National Trotting Association, 1892 Feb 10 (Box 50)
- Office list of entrees received to the Inaugural Louisville Prize (Box 50)
- Breeder and Sportsman (article about Electioneer's skeleton), 1891 Jun 17 (Box 51)
- Scrapbook of clippings, articles, and pamphlets concerning the Stock Farm and individual horses; includes one photograph and several loose letters (Box 52)
- Record book listing stallions, geldings, broodmares, colts, and fillies, with some notes re deaths, sales, and transfer between PASF and Vina, 1883-1887 (Box 53)
- Volumes (Box 54-56)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2017-332
  - Auction Catalogue of the Trotting Stock, Bred at Palo Alto Stock Farm, Santa Clara, California, The Property of Leland Stanford, 1890 (Box 1)